VIVEK GOPALAKRISHNAN

Massachusetts Institute of Technology 32 Vassar Street 32D-475BCambridge, MA 02139

vivekg@mit.edu https://vivekg.dev 3 eigenvivek 🖸

Research Overview

I am a third-year PhD candidate in Medical Engineering and Medical Physics at the Harvard-MIT Program in Health Sciences and Technology, advised by Dr. Polina Golland. The goal of my research is to address unmet clinical needs through the development of biomedical machine learning methods that deepen our ability to understand and treat disease. My current focus is on developing scalable synthetic data generation strategies to solve challenging problems in diagnostic and interventional radiology.

Research Areas: computer vision, 2D/3D reconstruction, image-quided surgery, image-based diagnostics.

Education

Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Ph.D. in Medical Engineering and Medical Physics

Johns Hopkins University

2020 - 2021 Advisors: Joshua Vogelstein and Carey Priebe

M.S.E. in Biomedical Engineering

2017 - 2021

2021 - Present

Advisor: Polina Golland

Johns Hopkins University B.S. in Biomedical Engineering

Research Experience

Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, MIT

2021 - Present

PhD student in the Medical Vision Group. Developed DiffDRR, a differentiable X-ray renderer and maintain an open-source PyTorch implementation with 100+ stars [C5]. Used DiffDRR to develop patient-specific 2D/3D registration algorithms with sub-millimeter accuracy [C6, C8]. Currently using synthetic X-rays to develop 3D image guidance systems for minimally invasive surgery and diagnostics for challenging diseases.

Xellar Biosystems, Newton, MA

Summer~2023

Discovered mechanisms by which supervised deep learning models in drug discovery cheat by exploiting confounding factors, and developed an interpretability metric to quantify the level of confounding [C7].

Department of Biomedical Engineering, Johns Hopkins University

2018-2021

Undergraduate researcher in the Neurodata Lab. Developed novel machine learning algorithms to analyze populations of graph-valued objects [C4, P1]. Applied these methods to discover neuroconnectively similar subtypes of autism spectrum disorder from multigraph connectomics data [C3].

Ragon Institute of MGH, MIT and Harvard, Cambridge, MA

Summer 2018

Developed predictive models of disease progression and immune recovery in HIV-positive children with TB co-infection using survival analysis [C2], and identified biomarkers for antiretroviral toxicity by applying machine learning methods to data from patients with HIV [C1].

Tufts University BioSeq Program, Somerville, MA

2016-2017

Proposed and conducted independent high school research using next-generation sequencing (NGS) to generate a novel human oral microbiome dataset. Analyzed NGS data to identify microbial markers of oral health. Presented at the 2017 Intel International Science and Engineering Fair.

Awards

Best Poster Award, MIT-MGB AI Cures Conference	2024
President's Innovation Award, Society of Biomolecular Imaging and Informatics	2023
Takeda Fellowship, MIT	2023
Neuroimaging Training Program Grant, MIT	2022
Provost's Undergraduate Research Award, Johns Hopkins University	2020
Joseph C. Pistritto Research Fellowship, Johns Hopkins University	2019
Second Place Winner, Microbiology, Intel International Science and Engineering Fair	2017
Semi-Finalist, Regeneron Science Talent Search	2017
Second Place Winner, Massachusetts State Science & Engineering Fair	2017
Second Place Winner, Massachusetts State Science & Engineering Fair	2016

Publications

Peer-Reviewed Papers

- C8 Vivek Gopalakrishnan, Neel Dey, and Polina Golland. "Intraoperative 2D/3D Image Registration via Differentiable X-ray Rendering". Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR), 2024. Best Poster Award at the MIT-MGB AI Cures Conference.
- C7 Vivek Gopalakrishnan, Jingzhe Ma, and Zhiyong Xie. "Grad-CAMO: Learning Interpretable Single-Cell Morphological Profiles from 3D Cell Painting Images". Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Workshops (CVPRW), 2024.
 President's Innovation Award from the Society of Biomolecular Imaging and Informatics.
- C6 Andrew Abumoussa, Vivek Gopalakrishnan, Benjamin Succop, Michael Galgano, Sivakumar Jaikumar, Yueh Lee, and Deb Bhowmick. "Machine Learning for Automated and Real-Time 2D-3D Registration of the Spine Using Only a Single Radiograph". Neurosurgical Focus, 2023.
- C5 Vivek Gopalakrishnan and Polina Golland. "Fast Auto-Differentiable Digitally Reconstructed Radiographs for Solving Inverse Problems in Intraoperative Imaging". Clinical Image-based Procedures, 2022.
- C4 Jaewon Chung, Eric Bridgeford, Jesus Arroyo, Benjamin D. Pedigo, Ali Saad-Eldin, Vivek Gopalakrishnan, Liang Xiang, Carey E Priebe, and Joshua T Vogelstein. "Statistical Connectomics". Annual Review of Statistics and Its Application, 2021.
- C3 Nian Wang, Robert J Anderson, David G Ashbrook, Vivek Gopalakrishnan, Youngser Park, Carey E Priebe, Yi Qi, Rick Laoprasert, Joshua T Vogelstein, Robert W Williams, and G Allan Johnson. "Variability and Heritability of Mouse Brain Structure: Microscopic MRI Atlases and Connectomes for Diverse Strains". NeuroImage, 2020.
- **C2 Vivek Gopalakrishnan**, Eliezer Bose, Usha Nair, Yuwei Cheng, and Musie Ghebremichael. "Pre-HAART CD4+ T-Lymphocytes as Biomarkers of Post-HAART Immune Recovery in HIV-Infected Children with or without TB Co-Infection". *BMC Infectious Diseases*, 2020.
- C1 Jong Soo Lee, Elijah Paintsil, Vivek Gopalakrishnan, and Musie Ghebremichael. "A Comparison of Machine Learning Techniques for Classification of HIV Patients with Antiretroviral Therapy-Induced Mitochondrial Toxicity from Those Without Mitochondrial Toxicity". BMC Medical Research Methodology, 2019.

Preprints

Vivek Gopalakrishnan, Jaewon Chung, Eric Bridgeford, Benjamin D. Pedigo, Jesús Arroyo, Lucy Upchurch, G. Allan Johnson, Nian Wang, Youngser Park, Carey E. Priebe, and Joshua T. Vogelstein. "Multiscale Comparative Connectomics". 2022.

Invited Talks

ilivited faiks	
Differentiable X-ray Rendering for Fast Intraoperative $2D/3D$ Image Registration	
 GE HealthCare AI, Bangalore, India MIT Visual Computing Seminar, Cambridge, MA 	$2024 \\ 2024$
Learning Interpretable Single-Cell Morphological Profiles from 3D Cell Painting Images	
• Society of Biomolecular Imaging and Informatics, Boston, MA	2023
Fast Auto-Differentiable DRRs: Quickly Solving Intraoperative Imaging Problems	
 Boston Medical Imaging Workshop, Brigham and Women's Hospital, Boston, MA Image-Guided Neurosurgery Meeting, Boston, MA Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Interventions CLIP, Singapore 	2022 2022 2022
Multiscale Comparative Connectomics	
 Presentations by Undergraduates in Life Sciences and Engineering Faculty-selected speakers from Johns Hopkins, Morgan State, and Coppin State University PathAI, Online Neuromatch Conference, Online 	2021 2021 2020
Teaching	
EN.BME.438/638 NeuroData Design II (Undergraduate/Graduate) Head Teaching Assistant, Johns Hopkins University	g 2021
EN.BME.437/637 NeuroData Design I (Undergraduate/Graduate) Head Teaching Assistant, Johns Hopkins University	1 2020
EN.BME.487 Computational Cardiology Laboratory (Undergraduate) Teaching Assistant, Johns Hopkins University Fal	1 2020
AS.MATH.201 Linear Algebra (Undergraduate) Teaching Assistant, Johns Hopkins University Fal	1 2020
Mentorship	
Undergraduate Students	
• Mohammadhossein Momeni, Truman State University *Co-supervised with Professor Sarah Frisken* Summer *Co-supervised with Professor Sarah Frisken*	r 2024
Service	
Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Medical Imaging Reviewer, Medical Imaging Computing and Computer Assisted Interventions (MICCAI) Reviewer, Medical Imaging with Deep Learning (MIDL) Reviewer, NeurIPS (Medical Imaging meets NeurIPS Workshop) Reviewer, ICLR (Neural Fields across Fields Workshop)	2024 2024 2024 2023 2023
Software	
DiffDRR: GPU-accelerated & auto-differentiable digitally reconstructed radiographs in PyTorch	2022

Primary author and maintainer (https://github.com/eigenvivek/DiffDRR/)